welcome back to lam rim and
i have a friend from shenzhen who
said that we miscalculated is it
true 1 equals tackle we don't count
march it's the realization that all living
beings were my mother second
then we remember all the good things
that my mother did for us then
[music]
we want to pay back then we
feel love then we feel
compassion for their problems and i forgot to
say the flag itself on moonduck and that
means we take personal responsibility and
then number 7 we are now on it this is the
result of the first six clear
no not clear
that is actually six and a half
before that we are now on seven
[music]
i like to read the tibetan time lam
rim and my teacher did it three times
and it helped me a lot again
i believe that this is the
greatest book i have ever written
in the tibetan language that's why a lot of the
classics that we study in mixed
nations are translations of Sanskrit they were not
originally written in tibetan and
Shastras of
time and commentaries also we have
sutras and tantras written in Sanskrit
about 999 and then three thousand
commentaries from India and
then the Tibetan tradition began
through four thousand tourists
books and this is the largest
collection of descriptions in the whole world.
Therefore, we are trying to catalog them
tens of thousands of books and this will take another 500
years. About
60 million pages have already been completed, but
we still have a lot to
go. So
if you want to study Tibetan and
open your mind to 300 thousand books on
spiritual classics, this is the
way to do this.
I will now plant a seed in you in three lives
and it will grow and
so we have now reached
tips.
Say kur-kur
means heavy, heavy load.
Her means to carry kur. Kir is to carry
something heavy.
What is the Sanskrit word for wife? Kur
in Sanskrit is borta. Perhaps, that's
why your name is that. I'm very sorry. Well, I
mean, cargo order comes from the same
word. That is, in ancient times, not in
such drilled as now, a
man had to carry his
wife on himself.  and so this person says but tell me
because I can't even guess that
I'm sure I can do it
now that I
understood everything with these planet-hopping things
well I don't know it seems to me it's a little bit beyond
my abilities
and
I'm not sure I can do it
[music]
100 dollars for the next phrase ran
lanier sam chirchike
clearly
stand 100 bucks for foam 99 98 no
that's a close guess
I heard what steel said
chin chi hee dont to take care of
one person even [ __ ] can't
take care of even one person there's a
picture for you guys
you want to take care of everyone damn I
can't even take care of myself properly
maybe two three I
don't know even one is hard for me I
can barely take care of myself you want me to take care of
everyone this is a
joke it's
really funny it's so true I
can't even pay my own bills
you want me to cry for everyone's bills
I actually
have trouble taking care of myself I
actually mean it sounds good to
me it seems  It sounds very noble to
take care of everyone, well, honestly,
honestly, I have never, I am
not able to take care of myself, I don’t know
about these other things,
by the way,
this is a definition for the floor, that is, it is a
functioning thing, this is a
technical definition in logic,
functioning things are that it is
capable of performing a function,
so what is
chak-chak, whole, then prostration, and literally
what this means is this: the
hand is
whole, it is to look for something, these are
again words for prostration in Tibetan, it
means to look
for a gift from your hands, breaking, that is, it is to look for a hearth, it is polite, I
know,
respectful for the hand, that is, it is to look for
something good from the hands of a teacher, that’s
what it means, whole means whether it is
Donetsk, any, whether something is a
woman, but
if someone who has such an
ability, I discovered this idea to try to
develop this ability, well, right now, to be
honest, I can’t even take care of one
person, I’m open to
possibilities, if you can show me
at least one person who can
do this, I tried
to see who can do this,
find at least one person who is
capable, and
if I find such a person, then I
will try to copy  their behavior and so
here's the
proposal well okay okay you
tell me take care of all living
beings I can't even take
care of myself but if you show me
someone who is capable of doing this well then I'll
introduce you to them
maybe I'll learn I'm open to learning
show me someone who can
do this and
then according to the bank rinpoche says okay
let's look at these super
capable people really strong in
this world you can find people who are
strong in this life there are people like me
I don't know there are famous politicians
famous Elon Musk there are special
such cool people
let's take their example
so here's their picture it's clear
in this picture there is more meaning than you
might think what a deep
what a deep meaning in the end they are
just dead meat all these Elon Musks
all super cool politicians
look strong but in the end
they are just
dead meat
very similar to meat they can live a little
better run faster collect more
money they can attack another country
in the end it's just dead meat they are
all the same
take these cool people
they are
exactly the same
helpless and they can't even take care
of themselves
[music]
these big
businessman these rich people
say well what about Elon Musk how about
these military
who have nuclear potential they
must be powerful hangar yes I am
just dead meat just dead meat
under the skin they have no more strength than you
you can't even provide yourself with a good mood
guess what happens to them they
can't either all this power that is in them
it's not that they are just meat that lives its
death just like mine that's
why it's funny bank rinpoche says I will
now
show you someone who can
take care of many people these
guys at the bank rent tea it's the same
they will end up just like everyone
else
and they will quickly be forgotten
there is nothing more frustrating in
the translations of ancient books than trying to
understand all these dead kings and their
sequence and all the time the same thing all
begins with the same
sentence the greatest king of all
time and people gura gura gura gura and so
on also died and
he tried to support the greatness of
such and such a kingdom and the kingdom
died and the people all died and  joys even
this city even died in which
where he taught pranks meant this is the
greatest city
this is how they
hanged New York Paris Moscow
all this is such a line in the book thing
Paris what is New York New York is
some kind of ruins need to be
found
near the Atlantic Ocean is located
there was this ancient Manhattan
always will be like this and give them I wonder
what about arhats
arhats are such powerful people what is the
definition of arhats we have the
gift of khata are those who forever
forever stopped their negative
emotions I always think about my younger
brother
we were four brothers in my family and
we were divided into older and younger and the
older lived in one room on a
bunk bed the younger in another and the
mission of the younger was to irritate the older and in
the morning they even said today I will
drive you crazy today I will really make you angry
and I thought well it's getting warmer especially
when you warned me you will never be able to
but they can always in  At the end of the day,
you eat, I'm already
very irritated, they laughed
at us, they said, "We've made it,
we've really
achieved our goal."
I always
thought that the definition of an arhat is a big
brother who's no longer angry at his younger
brothers because he's a person who
can no longer get angry. This
definition of an arhat is the one who's
dealt with all his
negative emotions, but it's not the same as dead
meat. They also can't help, they don't
really help other people. They
also die. Being an
arhat doesn't change your body.
They especially achieve nirvana, but that's not
enough to
really help other people.
[music]
They can't really help other
people that much. Somewhere in the cannons of time,
they can't yet
teach other people how not to
die. They themselves don't know yet. Even
nirvana isn't enough to help
other people.
Stems from turnover, a set of money for
where there's more negativity.
Rinpoche's bathhouse.
We begin to climb the ladder of spiritual
achievements. What's next? After an arhat,
created in
gardens,
this is the
first level of a bodhisattva. We have
only 10 levels.  Bodhisattvas, that is, the
day when you see emptiness directly,
you reach the
level called rab tam nko and
by definition, if you reach this
level, you have a battle chita, that is, you
achieve the introduction of direct emptiness and
bodhichitta directly and you are at the first
level subscribe and these guys can
help people
he says
some cool things they can do of course, but
compared to nods, this is a new
word for you guys think Tim has never
seen girls, so that means he has
one life left, that is, a
bodhisattva who has one life left
before he achieves enlightenment,
that is, a person who has reached the
1st level of bodhisattva and
compared with those who are 9 or 10th level
bodhisattvas, well, they can’t really
help that much, that is, I’d better look for a
person who is at level 9 or 10 than someone who
simply saw emptiness directly.
People who simply saw emptiness
can of course help well, but
compared to people who are half an hour away from
becoming Buddhas, I’d
better deal with the latter
and here it is written that you cannot
compare  and so what happens next
there are these people who have one
life left and between them there is someone
here great don't say
then oops then
try to imagine a person who
is living his last life sign
he will be a Buddha and in this life
not
they there a little
Hyun Joon this is
1 and one of the 12 signs of a real
monk
a real monk
why do they have this cool
robe this is actually their bed and
in the debates
it is also mentioned and no one
in the debates they lower it from the shoulder and all
that but no one now uses it for its
intended purpose no
one sleeps
on these
robes because in ancient times you did
not sleep in the monastery slept under the trees
in these monastic shawls that's why warm ones
were very popular and
so why is this mentioned here
because in the training shinki
[music]
silence this tree is correct what is it
than what that is that is
he has already sat under the tree of vodka
when he gets up he will already be a Buddha
you were there we were in Ohio and
I translated the sutra of the
diamond cutter and  I was sitting there where the
Buddha was. We went to Bulgaria. I sat on
my buttocks and placed it where the Buddha was.
And this Bodhi tree was above my
head.
I taught this sutra to various cutters,
and now he says, well, we have
this Bodhisattva who has only one life
left, but their ability to help you is
compared to
the guy who just
received direct perception of emptiness.
These guys are more useful compared to those guys,
and he says, well, not much. That
is, they haven't crossed that line yet. They
can't take care of infinite
beings yet. They are sitting
under the Bodhi tree,
but they haven't reached it yet. They haven't crossed
that line yet so they can
take care of everyone at the same time. They
just have a dad sitting under the tree. They are
sitting under this tree, and that is,
we start with that person in the office
who ca
n't even take care of herself.
Remember the picture? Then we talk about,
what about these cool politicians? They are
also
dead meat. What about these arhats?
Yes, they are cool, of course, but they are still
dead meat.  and these bodhisattvas, yes, they are cool,
but they
can't even compare these guys with those
guys who have almost achieved
enlightenment and have only
one life left, they say no,
but even cooler, of course, are those who have already
sat under a tree and will soon achieve
enlightenment, but compared to the Buddhas,
they are of course also useless, the
first soup means not having patience and the
operas of soup is an
idiom that means incomparable, of all these
cool people, I will
choose only the fully enlightened,
but he says, that is, those who have already
achieved enlightenment, an
army of soup, and
then look at this picture, this is how you will
remember
if you compare
[music]
the area of ​​the universe with
the space of this palm, that is the
difference, that is, the person who I became
enlightened who stood up
after sitting under a tree, here I am
[music]
his abilities are
comparable, a palm is a thrill compared to the
area of ​​the entire universe, the space of the
entire universe, that is, even arhats, even
the one who saw emptiness directly or
only one life left for him until
enlightenment, is he already sitting even under a
tree  Vodka of all these people's
abilities is like one palm and as soon as
you cross this line
you become a fully enlightened
Buddha then your abilities are like an
infinite universe not
they are equal the space of the universe
he says here where you are going no need to
trifle what is nirvana aria arhat
nonsense let's
follow the really cool guys
because then their abilities are not
limited the number of
people that we they can help is not limited
he goes we
exclude and here is an important description of the
abilities of Buddha they say tell
Shindo that is
often and
not the name Tibetan
Kesha Kesha
supra in Wisconsin his
name is sesame
he it means the
ability
to manifest something at the moment when you
need without during meditation
that is someone
someone
in Texas and
[music]
they have a problem you immediately
find yourself there did
not understand what is happening in Texas
Minsk Andrey means you just manifest
put
in the
next car someone broke down they
fix their tire and you are already in the next
car you stop and
help  and
the next for example
one day
[music]
someone's car with in
this in this area in Texas I
broke it didn't break it fell off a cliff and
suddenly another car was driving stopped and
helped get out
at any moment in the universe when someone
needs you once and you're there that would be
cool really that's it
try to imagine
that if
someone breaks down breaks their car in
Texas
if it is in another universe
it doesn't matter because you are always in
all places at the same time
[music]
what if at the same moment it
happens in different places it doesn't matter
because you can appear in different
places so that about other places it doesn't
matter how many that would be
cool that would be great this is
called bodhicitta let me be a
service to
help
all broken tires in the universe
let me always be in the next not
suggestion I will help fix the ring but
the flat one and
[music]
this means
repairing all the tires of all the cars
at the same time in the universe that's a good
example that's right
all the flat tires in the entire universe
can be subordinated at the same time that's already
something and
you need to think like this when you
think about distinguishing and
because now you are limited to one
physical body you are not now you
think that you can help one
person
at this moment you need to overcome this
limitation
stop thinking that you can help
someone you can think whether I can
automatically help everyone at the same time
in different bodies and that's cool that's
already something
try to imagine it and then it will
help you achieve this state of mind
I would like to fix everyone's flat tires
at the same time
I would like to fix all the cabins of Diamond
Mountain where with at the same time and clean
I don't know who cleaned my cabin well I am
very
grateful for this it
looks very beautiful thank you
I am blessed that there are special people around me
so only Buddha is a
universal
person who repairs all the flat tires
in the universe
so
returning to the teachings about taking
refuge we taught you how a dish can
help you if you go to refuge
take refuge and he says now
change it the other way
Buddha says
this is who I am that is he
says if you want to have
fun
return to the teachings and  refuge and
look from the point of view of the person
who teaches me from the point of view of the
person who needs help
not
knocking and the point of view of the
person who takes refuge in the
Buddha dharma sanki he says from the point of
view of the Buddha you may want to
return to these
teachings and all these cool things
that the Buddha is able to do for you
if you are in trouble now think how it is
if you are this person and so guess what
grandfather did I came back and took
this list for you from there I
think
that
you need to prepare I have a tele
that takes me everywhere and I can
prepare that is if it says here
that
you should
find this passage you really
should do it so not only did I find the
list but also picked up a picture and so the
first picture of themes
here
this picture is that you are beyond any
fear the
first quality of refuge
that is before this was and take
refuge in the Buddha they are beyond any fear
now this take refuge in me I am
beyond any fear
put yourself
ok this is on this cliff I never
climb such cliffs because I
know  that I will be the first one under whom this
rock will collapse well imagine
what we are talking about here there is
nothing to be afraid of nothing scares you
even death that is you will be like this
who is not afraid of anything
this will connect that is instead of the refuge
that
weaklings accept
now you are bodhichitta I am the same I am
not afraid of anything I can help everyone I
can fix your wheel
2 with this
[music]
10 cents
skillful means slippers
why are we showing this Parker I
like the word here does it
mean
active or something a person who can
do some special things
that I will do this I will do this I will do this that is
Buddha is super effective
will solve a
person who solves problems that is
he frees other people from fear
they are super creative their mind is like a
super computer and if someone has
problems he is like chick chick fixed everything
Buddha is so special I
diptyque
search engine solution to all problems a
person who is looking for a
solution to all problems and
some say I have a problem and
he is like don't worry I will help
well  who comes to you like that
you just
[music]
just earned 600 thousand dollars
this week someone comes to you and
can I ask you for 200 dollars you
yes no problem
that is
2 the
second quality is a super flexible solution to
all problems of
bullets using all art
artificial means for anything that
people need
I know that you need to do business this
business this business they save you from
all your problems here is the
third quality
[music]
my god my wife
my wife's son has a dog and you
devote such for everyone there is he has a
dog that always wags its tail in front of everyone
and so
it is
equal to sleep and compassion and love for all
people and moderate as
far as the sky
[music]
this is the definition of a difference
not a meter
[music]
this means immeasurable equal clarity
action at po iksha
outside outside
difference once a day
[music]
differences
that do not pay attention to
differs that is, I am
not able to
distinguish people
someone closer someone further that is the
third quality will be that is the
same they circled
well and  I guess
they don't have favorites when it comes to licking either.
If you
are a human being at all, they
trust you and lick you. You know, there are
dogs that lick everyone and
influence everyone with their tail. That is, this is the quality of
Buddha, equal love for all living
beings. And
there are such people. Have you met them? You
try to hit them, they
don't lick your feet, it's the same.  oh
wagging and so how many do we have in quality there
are four more yes ok
and
this
[music]
waitress who
treats all customers equally well
regardless of tips this is a
specific quality of Buddha as a
refuge is that they treat
all people equally no matter how they
treat will this is they them you will
treat them badly shouting travaux
they appreciate you praise or
massage you or vice versa take
blows anyway you treat equally
no matter whether you did something good
for them did how is this a joke
[music]
joke this
remember do you remember that I told you that the
money I
gave you last year I will remember after this
Buddha they are not like that at all that is
they will not ask such a question even
if they know where this
waitress is I needed to find
several photos in the price so we
have a cafe and there is no one
in this cafe no customers no
work no workers so in this
sense it is joyful
she smiles at them and does not care whether
she gets a tip or not I don't care
she will still
treat them equally well yes
The last quality of water, let's
go through the pictures again,
we will have three classes today,
let's just look at these pictures and
then we will have a little
extra time, I
will go through the next class, the
first was a guy with glasses and at the
computer,
tell me what this means, it means I
can't even take care of myself, this is a
rhetorical question, and I am not even
able to take care of myself,
you want me to take care of all
people, this is probably a joke, this is the first thing to
remember from this class, you poison them with do
n't
think badly of yourself, no one else
can take care of everyone,
don't think badly of yourself either, everyone is not a Buddha,
including Aryans, Arhats, and even people
who are already sitting under the Bodhi tree
but have not yet achieved enlightenment, they are all the
same, they look strong, but they are
dead meat,
guess why,
because no one in this regard is
capable of taking better care of other
people, including even Arhats,
even those who have achieved nirvana, in
fact, cannot take care of
all people
completely, the next picture, what is it like,
palms of the hand,
comparisons with the entire surface of
the universe, this is  It's the same as comparing an
ordinary person or any of these
compared to what a Buddha can do,
that is,
the abilities between these people and a Buddha
are comparable to the area of ​​the palm of a hand from the
area of ​​the entire universe and then he
says,
return four to these four things
that make a Buddha a worthy object
for refuge and
then turn it over to the other side and
feel how good it is that you will become
this now we are not talking about
taking refuge about being a
refuge he has a cool quality the
first quality is complete fearlessness
nothing can ever
scare you even death an
absolute
absolute threat for you is meaningless
because you have surpassed death someone
says I will kill you and you say such a thing no you can't
because I have already
surpassed this what else can bother you
I will steal your wallet there I
have access to the Moscow Ring Road I
have access to the wealth of the universe
like that take my wallet okay I
will take another 10 million in the next five
minutes
everything is fine with me we take the wallet
imagine that you have  these
abilities you will be fearless
next topic
you can
focus on the word hey man plaster and
ideas super-computer is a super flexible
computer that solves all problems
any problem that
people would turn to you with you are
not a problem
they are like this
because when you turned to him
they already knew the answer that they would
give you before we asked but they are
still playing this game you ask
they where you need to think and I know to do it
by the way don't forget when you become a
Buddha it
should it is such politeness you need to
observe this interval so as not to
answer the question immediately
delay next merin mipo
they do not feel that someone is close to them
someone far away does not feel that everyone is close to them
everyone is close to them they do
not feel that someone is closer to them
someone further
they love everyone equally equally and a
promise and therefore and the last and
they do not care
do not care what you will do in return to them
give or thank
if you want to do a good business
you need to be by the way prepared to
receive a certain number of
blows for saving someone's lives they  they hit
you and in this too the clarity is equal they don't care whether
you pay them or not whether you
praise them or not they don't care how
you treat them they
will still help you they are predetermined in this
and this is a wonderful way
to live your life and you help people
without expectation even if they harm you
okay here's a little more money here's a
little more for free if we want to
achieve this state when we don't
care what people think of you and
still help this is a very wonderful
place such a place in which we can
be
[music]
you again
made a mess in the booth that I calculated for
you ok
no big deal I'll
take it again I decided in the next lesson
we will talk
about this behavior service to others it doesn't
matter what people do to you and thank you
and see you in the next lesson